<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic</title>
    <link>https://wheelern.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://wheelern.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Academic</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©NJ Wheeler 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://wheelern.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Academic</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genetic and functional diversification of chemosensory pathway receptors in mosquito-borne filarial nematodes</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/wheeler2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/wheeler2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gene drives for schistosomiasis transmission control</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/maier2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/maier2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New insights into neglected diseases</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/uww2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/uww2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vSv-L38cWf2vK1Mnq9l9616exrq9HshfbpSJffPnl8qs8lUU2XmJqB3hR0wqk166g/embed?start=false&amp;loop=false&amp;delayms=3000&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;389&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progress toward transgenesis in Biomphalaria glabrata and implications for snail control.</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/gsa2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/gsa2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helminth and Vector Genomics</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/project/genomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/project/genomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This page is a work in progress!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequence and structural variation in the genome of the Biomphalaria glabrata embryonic (Bge) cell line</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/wheeler2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/wheeler2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progress toward transgensis in Biomphalaria glabrata</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/schisto_symposium2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/schisto_symposium2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vTxTTa-EixbpWBv8G_R5vHRRKtGv26brnbaf2XpUbTQnsp1-F_hI-Ss9GxvNXpIhqsR3yqX89AYa64i/embed?start=false&amp;loop=false&amp;delayms=3000&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;389&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helminth Chemosensation and Migration</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/project/chemosensation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/project/chemosensation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This page is a work in progress!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helminth GPCRs</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/project/gpcrs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/project/gpcrs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost all anthelmintics (drugs used to treat helminth infections in humans and animals) target ion channels (see this 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_anthelminticdrugs/anthelminticdrugs.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WormBook article&lt;/a&gt; for more information on anthelmintics and their targets). Ion channels are often fast acting signal transduction channels that operate at the neuromuscular junction and are often activated by neurotransmitters such as acetylcholine, serotonin, dopamine, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One motiviating hypothesis that we have is that the next-generation of anthelmintics will target GPCRs instead of ion channels. Currently, only two drugs, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cell.com/trends/parasitology/pdf/S1471-4922%2818%2930009-6.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;praziquantel&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs00436-005-1438-z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;emodepside&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; target G protein-coupled receptors (GPCRs), but they likely aren&amp;rsquo;t their only targets. Unfortunately, there hasn&amp;rsquo;t been a novel anthelmintic developed in decades, and we think a focus should be given to new receptor targets like GPCRs. GPCRs are classically believed to be more slow acting than ion channels and function in sensitive neuromodulation, but that isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily true for helminths. Neuropeptides can cause direct muscular contraction through a GPCR, and so can neurotransmitters [Day and Ribeiro citations].&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adapting tools from free-living nematodes to study chemosensory pathways in filarial nematode parasites</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/chawm2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/talk/chawm2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vR8ier14rq7frxayGcPTpvjIHy1VCOafXMS0tSafPVS2cfup185DAJ8w4nY6Y86rf3E0IecWat-jRq4/embed?start=false&amp;loop=false&amp;delayms=3000&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;389&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tissue-specific transcriptome analyses provide new insights into GPCR signalling in adult Schistosoma mansoni</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/hahnel2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/hahnel2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snail Transgenesis</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/project/snail_transgenesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/project/snail_transgenesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Schistosomiasis is a widespread and burdensome neglected tropical disease (NTD) that inflicts massive morbidity on the world’s poorest and most vulnerable people. This infection, caused by parasitic flatworms of the genus &lt;em&gt;Schistosoma&lt;/em&gt;, is increasingly controlled by mass drug administration (MDA) of praziquantel (PZQ), which is effective at quickly clearing adults from the patient’s vasculature. Regional and nationalized intervention through MDA has substantially reduced the global burden of schistosomiasis in the past +20 years, but a prevalence of nearly 200 million remains. The 2012 London Declaration on NTDs initiated a collaboration between public and private entities, including Merck KGaA, that set a goal to control schistosomiasis by 2020. This will primarily be achieved by the spread and optimization of MDA, but recent models show that the collaboration will likely fall short unless MDA is greatly expanded in high prevalence areas. Such an expansion would increase the already significant fear of the proliferation of PZQ resistance in local &lt;em&gt;Schistosoma&lt;/em&gt; spp. populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These fears scaffold the argument that schistosomiasis control ought to have an integrated, multifaceted approach that includes MDA, education, and vector control. Control of the freshwater snail vector of Schistosoma spp., including species of the genera &lt;em&gt;Biomphalaria&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bulinus&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Oncomelania&lt;/em&gt;, has classically been performed by biological agents, molluscicidal treatment, or habitat reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advent of genome editing technology has enabled the development of new methods of vector control. Using CRISPR/Cas9 genome editing in combination with the endogenous homologous repair mechanism and incorporation of synthetic repair templates, gene drives can be designed to spread synthetic constructs throughout a vector population through super-Mendelian inheritance. If the chosen trait is deleterious for the organism, the trait will be driven to fixation and the population will slowly crash (population suppression). Likewise, if the trait confers resistance to the pathogen such that it cannot properly develop, the pathogen will be unable to continue its life cycle and have its infective stage transmitted to the human host (population replacement). These ideas have primarily been promulgated as a control measure for pests or insects that bear parasitic and viral pathogens, but the idea has recently been suggested as a new measure for snail control. Unfortunately, the methods for transgenesis that are necessary for such techniques are not standard in snails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Merck Global Health Institute, in collaboration with researchers from the University of Wisconsin-Madison and other consultants, has undertaken the task of developing the tools to achieve the aim of genome editing in &lt;em&gt;B. glabrata&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional analysis of Girardia tigrina transcriptome seeds pipeline for anthelmintic target discovery.</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/wheeler2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/wheeler2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel RNAi-mediated approach to G protein-coupled receptor deorphanization: proof of principle and characterization of a planarian 5-HT receptor.</title>
      <link>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/zamanian2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://wheelern.github.io/publication/zamanian2012/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
